Guide to the Eugene Gordon Photograph Collection 1960-1989 PR 248
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
Eugene Gordon Photograph Collection
1960-1989
PR 248
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
3.0 Linear feet
The Eugene Gordon Photograph Collection contains black & white gelatin silver prints from 1970-1990 (bulk 1975-1980). The photos depict street life, religious groups, buildings and public events of New York City.
Provenance
Gift given in two parts: Eugene Gordon, 2005 & Miriam Gordon, 2008.
Access
The collection is open to qualified researchers. Portions of the collection that have been photocopied or microfilmed will be brought to the researcher in that format; microfilm can be made available through Interlibrary Loan.
Permission to Reproduce
Application to use images from this collection for publication should be made in writing to the Department of Rights and Reproductions, The New-York Historical Society, 170 Central Park West, New York, NY 10024. Permission to reproduce or quote text from this collection in a publication must be requested from and granted in writing by the Library Director, The New-York Historical Society, 170 Central Park West, New York, NY 10024.
Biographical Note
Eugene Gordon started his career as a photographer, taking stock images for textbooks and other publications. He traveled extensively in his personal life and documented religious ceremonies and different ethnicities of people in the countries he visited. Gordon continued this project throughout New York City, but most extensively at home in Queens, New York. Some of his favorite subjects to document were street scenes, parades, festivals, and Times Square. He printed his photographs in his own darkroom in Forest Hills, Queens.
Scope and Contents Note
The Eugene Gordon Photograph Collection contains black & white gelatin silver prints from 1970-1990 (bulk 1975-1980) of street life, religious groups, buildings, and public events of New York City. In general, the photographs show New Yorkers going about their lives in a vibrant city. Gordon's images highlight the shifting ethnic makeup of NYC.
Street Views includes general views of city life as well as more specific attempts to document neighborhoods. Many of the photographs of Times Square juxtapose adult theater marquees with business people or document the often hand-drawn massage parlor signs common to the area in the 1970s and 1980s. Gordon's eye for the absurd and ironic is evidenced by one photo that depicts a man sleeping on the sidewalk in front of a street mission sign that proclaims "Jesus Saves." Photographs of Harlem highlight street-front churches as well as restaurants and stores.
Views of neighborhoods of the outer boroughs focus on the ethnicities of their inhabitants. In the case of Jackson Heights and Flushing, the multi-ethnic mix of residents is emphasized; a photograph shows the sign of a medical practice with surnames of at least four different nations represented. Photos of Greenpoint, Brooklyn depict broken down cars and buildings. Photographs of Long Island City include several views across the East River, looking toward the United Nations.
Miscellaneous views include an exterior shot of an outdoor ballet rehearsal at Lincoln Center, the Fresh Kills Landfill in Staten Island, and a southerly view showing the buildings along 59th Street.
Buildings includes several photographs of the demolition of St. Peter's Lutheran Church to make way for the erection of the Citicorp Building on Lexington Avenue between 53rd and 54th Streets. Views of the United Nations show the statue beating the sword into a plowshare, gifted by the Soviet Union. Building interiors include the Metropolitan Opera.
Events includes parades, festivals, and exhibitions. Photos show the outdoor food carts of Little Italy's San Genaro Festival in 1974. This heading includes photos which were taken during the August 26, 1970 Women's Strike for Equality demonstration and parade. They show women and some men walking down Fifth Avenue. Women of all ages and races are represented in these photos, as are many of the humorous and/or angry signs they carried. Photos of the 1988 Lesbian and Gay Pride Parade show participants with a "Free Sharon Kowalski" banner. A comic book exhibit held in the Hotel Biltmore in the early 1980s is also documented. Other photos show an anti-Apartheid rally, and an election rally for Michael Dukakis, the 1988 presidential candidate.
Religious Groups contains small photo essays on some of New York City's religious groups and communities. Gordon asked to photograph these ceremonies and was granted access. Hare Krishnas are shown worshipping in the Rada Krishna Temple in Brooklyn, as well as selling literature and singing in the streets of Manhattan. Gordon documented a congregation of Sikhs worshipping at the Gurdwara Sikh Cultural Society of New York in Flushing, Queens.
Subjects includes a variety of scenes that do not fit neatly into the above headings. They include photos on subjects as diverse as auctions, construction scenes with unidentifiable locations, a pet cemetery, traffic court, food related and drug related images.
Arrangement
The collection is ordered into five series.
Series I: Street Views
Series II: Buildings
Series III: Events
Series IV: Religious Groups
Series V: Subjects
Advertising -- United States; Bronx (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Coney Island (New York, N.Y.); Food -- United States; Graffiti; Lincoln Center; Little Italy (New York, N.Y.); New York (N.Y.) -- Buildings, structures, etc; New York (N.Y.) -- Social life and customs; New York City-Cemetery; New York Stock Exchange; Political rallies; Sikh Americans; Staten Island (New York, N.Y.); Street photograpy; Times Square (New York, N.Y.)
- Series I: Street Views
  - Subseries I: Bronx
    - The Bronx, 1984-1987 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Subseries II: Brooklyn
    - Brighton Beach, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Greenpoint, 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Miscellaneous Brooklyn, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Subseries III: Manhattan
    - 9th Avenue, 1985-1990 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 14th Street, 1982-1986 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Central Park, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Chinatown, 1985-1988 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Coney Island, 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - East Village, 1984-1988 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Greenwich Village, 1986-1988 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Harlem, 1986-1988 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Lower East Side, 1982-1990 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Midtown, 1986-1989 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Times Square, 1982-1988 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Times Square, 1982-1988 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Union Square, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Washington Square, 1986-1987 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Subseries IV: Queens
    - Astoria, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Flushing, 1984-1987 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Forest Hills, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Jackson Heights, 1982-1986 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - JFK Airport, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Long Island City, 1982-1987 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Subseries V: Staten Island
    - Fresh Kills Landfill, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Subseries VI: Miscellaneous
    - Misc. Street Scenes, 1985-1990 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Misc. Street Scenes, 1985-1990 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Series II: Buildings
  - Lincoln Center, 1984-1988 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - New York Stock Exchange, 1982-1986 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - (Demolition of) Saint Peter's Church (53rd & Lexington), 1982-1985 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Sirovich Day Center, 1982-1985 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - United Nations, 1982-1990 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Building Interiors, 1985-1988 (Box 3, Folder 33)
- Series III: Events
  - Anti-Apartheid Rally 9/13/1995, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Comic Book Exhibit, Biltmore Hotel, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Election Related, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Hunter Mountain, Mountain Eagle Festival, 1985-1986 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    Auctions; Brighton Beach; Bronx (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Comic Book Exhibit, Biltmore Hotel; Construction; Courts -- New York (State) -- New York; Drug Abuse; Elections; Food -- United States; Food: Street Vendors and Meat Packing; Greenpoint; Hare Krishnas; Homeless; Lesbian & Gay Pride Parade; Lincoln Center; New York City-Cemetery; New York Stock Exchange; Pet Cemetery; Photos of Print Advertisements; Political rallies; San Genaro Festival, Little Italy; Sikhs; Sirovich Day Center; Spanish Harlem 3 Kings (Epiphany) Parade; St. Patrick's Day Parade; St. Peter's Church; Staten Island (New York, N.Y.); Times Square (New York, N.Y.); Traffic Court; TWA Strike, LaGuardia Airport; United Nations Building; Women's Strike for Equality
  - Lesbian & Gay Pride Parade, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Saint Patrick's Day Parade, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - San Genaro Festival, Little Italy, 1982-1985 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Spanish Harlem 3 Kings (Epiphany) Parade, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Misc. Parades (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - TWA Strike, LaGuardia Airport, 1986-1988 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Women's Strike for Equality, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Misc. Events, 1985-1989 (Box 4, Folder 45)
- Series IV: Religious Groups
  - Hare Krishnas, 1982-1985 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Sikhs, Flushing, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Sikhs, Richmond Hill, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Misc. Religious, 1984-1986 (Box 4, Folder 49)
- Series V: Subjects
  - Auctions, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Construction, 1985-1990 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Drug Related, 1987-1988 (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Food: Street Vendors & Meat Packing, 1982-1986 (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - "The Homeless", 1986-1989 (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - Pet Cemetery, 1986-1987 (Box 4, Folder 55)
  - Photos of Newspaper Clippings & Advertisements, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 56)
  - Traffic Court, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 57)